Welcome to this Business Central launch
event presentation about what's new in
AL Go for GitHub.
So, what is AL Go for GitHub? Well, AL
Go for GitHub is the plug-and-play
DevOps solution for Business Central
development on GitHub.
Um it offers you like a an easy-to-use
DevOps solution where Business Central
developers can do secure CI/CD and and
and include like quality assurance uh
change tracking, validation of of of
code um
and and all of the things that you would
expect from a modern and and and uh
and comprehensive DevOps solution.
The difference here is that you don't
need any knowledge in Docker,
PowerShell, or YAML, or anything like
that. You don't need a dedicated DevOps
engineer. It's a tool that you can use.
It's not an investment area per se.
So, this presentation is not really
about how easy it is to get started on
all of these things because this
presentation is all about
if you are already using AL Go for
GitHub, so what's new? Um I will touch
upon what if you haven't seen AL Go for
GitHub yet, uh then I will urge you to
go to this URL, aka.ms/ALGoWorkshop.
Let's click on this one and see what it
is.
And just briefly uh show you what we
have here. So, this is a workshop that
takes you through like introduction,
prerequisite, get started uh how to
create your first AL Go repository,
basically taking you through all the
steps that you need in order to get set
up with Algo for GitHub and then
choose the next step like add an app and
and and then
do all of the different workflows that
it takes
in order to get started with Algo for
GitHub. But again, this presentation is
very much about if you're already set up
with Algo for GitHub, you've been using
it and and now you kind of
you want to know what's new, what can I
take advantage of of new features and
stuff like that. Uh and that is what
this session is all about. So, the
topics for today
is
I'll talk about settings and updating.
So, it's a question I've gotten a lot
from partners like where are my settings
and how do I upgrade to the latest
version and stuff like that. So, I'm
going to cover that um
even though nothing really changed in
that.
Code signing of apps uh
a lot of things changed in the code
signing segment. Not really in Algo
because it's like just automated, but
the way you set it up is slightly
changed.
Uh
there are some deployment enhancements
and uh the possibility of doing custom
deployment now.
Uh
pull request status check, compiler
folder Linux and and something called
the GH token workflow. I'm going to
uh talk about those things as well and
then at the end
uh let's look about look into to the
future and see what's coming um
in the future or what might be coming in
the future actually.
Let's talk about settings and upgrading.
So, where are your settings? What
version are you running and how do I
upgrade to the latest version? So,
settings.
Algo for GitHub is as I said at the
beginning a plug-and-play DevOps
solution. Now, you don't have to modify
settings. Probably if you just set up
Algo and add your app and add your
source code, it might just work for you.
You might not have to change any
settings at all.
But if you are to modify anything in
Algo for GitHub, you don't do it by
writing code, you do it by changing
settings. Um
you can you can go
and see all the settings that are there.
Uh but but then where in your repository
do you put the settings and and and
which settings are are what? So, there
are three types of settings in AL Go for
GitHub really. There's repository wide
settings. These settings like
uh
uh like the template URL, there's
schedules for workflows, there's what
are your GitHub runners, there's the
environments, they're not like app or
project specific, anything like that.
These things are settings that cover the
entire repository.
If your repository only contains one
project, then whether you put things in
repository settings or project settings
doesn't really matter because there's
only one project. If, however, you have
a setup where you have
uh
a repository with multiple projects,
then you might have project wide
settings,
which are
placed in the project folder. Like the
.al go folder specifies where the
project is. And these project settings
could be like
app folders, it could be project name,
it could be dependencies,
uh the artifacts using, the country or
your targeting this project for.
Uh
and then so so so the repository is the
global settings, the project is the
individual project. have any settings
per app per se. You have like the
app.json where you can specify stuff,
but that's not AL Go settings, that's
app specific uh stuff. You do also have
workflow specific settings. The workflow
specific settings
are also on the repository level. It is
stuff like when you're running the test
next main major or test next minor, uh
what what settings do you want to have
um when you're running these things. So,
three levels, repository, project, and
workflow.
And what do you have in those?
As I already said, the repository wide
ones,
and and then you actually also have
another layer on top of that, and that's
repository and organizational variables.
The settings in those is repository
settings. So,
you you you don't have variables per
project per se, you you you only have
variables for for for the repo or for
the
for the organization. Let's just look
into one of these areas. Let's click on
this one to see the repository settings.
So, this one is an AL Go repo settings
with an artifact specification. So, this
is an example of
the setting for that one, but if you go
into the GitHub folder here, you'd find
the AL Go settings file. This is the
repository settings. And then the dot AL
Go, you will have the project settings.
If we have multiple project, we have
multiple folders with multiple dot AL Go
folders underneath that. And that is
where the project settings then would
be. So, this is where you find settings.
This is
how to get forward with that.
What version of AL Go are you running?
In the template URL in your repo
settings, in the dot GitHub AL Go
settings,
is a URL that points to the template
that you created the repository from.
It's probably
github.com/microsoft/ALGoPTE
or AppSource
at main. The at main is the branch or
the version that you're running. If you
specify at main, means that you will
just have the latest version. But, what
is the latest version? Well,
if you look into the initialize
workflow details in any of the
workflows,
you will see the version number
specified there. AL Go for GitHub
version 3.2.
Um if you are running the preview
version,
that would the template URL would be
github.com microsoft AL Go PTE at
preview,
then
the initialize would say preview.
Uh so so this is the way that to find
when like if you have an issue, you
create an issue on GitHub, and and I'll
ask you we'll ask you, so what version
are you running? Well,
go and look in in in the uh
in in the in the output and and you'll
find it there. And we might say to you,
please
install the latest update of AL Go for
GitHub. And the way you do that is by
running an workflow called upgrade AL Go
system files.
The way you know that you have updates
available is that every time you have a
CI CD or build running, there'll be a
job called check for updates. The check
for updates job will will be like
checking whether there's any updates and
it will give you a warning saying there
are updates for your AL Go system. Run
uh update AL Go system files workflow to
download the latest version.
Um
in order to do that, you need a secret
called GH token workflow that contains a
personal access token uh with
permissions to modify workflows. When
you've done that, you can run that
workflow called update AL Go system
files and you will get the the latest
version. The direct commit question
here, if you say yes to that, uh you
will it you the the latest version of AL
Go for GitHub will be directly committed
into your branch. If you say no, it will
create a pull request. If you have set
up branch protection, you might need to
create a pull request there.
So that's it.
Um
settings, version, all of these things,
we should have that in place.
Now, about the new things, like code
signing.
A lot of questions we've had lately is
that does AL Go for GitHub support code
signing with the private key in an HSM
key storage?
And yes, we do.
So, looking at code signing anno 2023,
earlier this year, there was a
actually last year, there was an
announcement that July 1st this year,
all code signing certificate
that are issued by code signing by the
providers of code signing certificates,
will have to deliver the
private key in a hardware module or an
HSM
key storage. So, that might be a
USB token or
or a HSM key vault.
Um, what we did in AL Go for GitHub was
to
add support for
HSM key storage in Azure Key Vault. That
is a special skew of the key vault that
you can purchase and then you will have
the ability to get your
code signing certificate delivered in in
your key vault and then you just have to
set up the connection from AL Go for
GitHub to your key vault and then we'll
perform the the
the code signing of your app through
that one. I don't have a
a demo of this because I don't have a
code signing certificate, but we have
multiple partners who already managed to
set that up so that that it it works
fine.
Deployment enhancements is one of the
the bigger things in this release.
So,
deployment done the right way.
We in AL Go for GitHub support GitHub
environments. So, in GitHub you can set
up environments for
for your repository that you want to
deploy to to these environments. These
environments
you can have branch policies, meaning
that you you can only deliver to
to this environment if you are in the
main branch or
whatever.
We have a new setting called exclude
environments where you can exclude some
of the environments from deploying if
you have like system environments or
GitHub pages and stuff like that.
And lastly,
if you have a free school,
if you have like the the the free GitHub
and you have private repositories in
that one, environments is is is not
available in private repository in the
free GitHub school.
And then you can define the environments
in settings. So, you have
basically an environment setting called
a setting called environments.
Where you can list the environments that
you have. So,
that is the definition of the
environments that you want to deploy to,
like the the list of GitHub environments
plus the list of of environments in
settings minus the environments you have
in exclude environments.
Um after that,
we need to now figure out what is the
real name of these environments.
Uh
earlier we had secrets, like you could
specify environment name
environment name. Like if you had a QA
environment, it would be QA
environment name. And then you'd create
a secret with that
environment. The problem was that
Uh and and the the reason why we
selected secrets here was that you could
create those as secrets underneath the
environment in GitHub. The problem with
this is that if you have that as a
secret, then GitHub will like mask any
value and you cannot transfer the value
from one job to the other. And a lot of
things would fail if your environment
name was something that was used in
other locations. So, we had to like
revert back from that and the real way
of of doing this going forward is to
create a new setting called deploy to an
environment name, meaning deploy to Q&A,
and that setting would then include all
the things that that would be like
relevant to set up for that environment,
including some of the things that were
requested by some partners like sync
mode, continuous deployment and stuff
like that.
So the this is an example of
the deploy to QA in version four of
Elvanto GitHub. You have an environment
type. Default is SAS. Environment name,
this yeah, the default is actually the
same as the environment name
that you have on on GitHub. So in this
case it would be Q&A. Branches, default
would be just main.
Projects, default would be star, meaning
all projects that you
um have in in your
in your repository.
And then the sync mode can be force sync
or
I think clean or add. It's in in the
settings in the documentation you can
see that.
And then there's a setting called
continuous deployment.
Whether you want to use this environment
for continuous deployment. In earlier
versions we would deduct the continuous
deployment from the name. So if your
environment name was
uh QA, we would automatically roll out
continuous deployment to that one. If it
was QA  prod, then we would
say, "Oh, that's a production
environment, so we're not going to touch
that."
Uh now
it's still the way to default deduct
what is continuous deployment, but if
you create a deploy to QA environment
and set continuous deployment, you can
set it to true or false, no matter
whether it's a
it's a production environment or a
um
or a sandbox environment. So you can
actually set up continuous deployment to
a production environment if you have
like uh a final acceptance test that is
a prod environment, then by all means go
ahead and run continuous deployment to
that one.
Um
runs on is what GitHub runner do you
want to use for deploying to this
environment? The default is probably
Windows latest, but you can set it to
Ubuntu latest or other things. Uh
why is this? So why do we have an
environment type when we only deploy to
SaaS? Why do we have a runs on when it
just like
um installs the
app on an online service? Well,
the reason for that is really another
newcomer in in this version, which is
custom deployment.
Do it your way. So
custom deployment
If you specify environment type in your
environment setting,
then that determines the mechanism used
for deploy. So if you say the
environment type is
on prem or custom or whatever, then
we'll say, "Okay, it's no longer a SaaS
environment, so our deployment mechanism
will no longer be used."
Um then you can write a custom script,
and you just place that in the dot
GitHub folder, deploy deploy to and then
environment type.ps1.
Uh and we will then
uh
create a structure of parameters that
we'll transfer to you, and you can
actually see the parameters on the
right-hand side here
uh with continuous deployment, auth
context, environment type, runs on, and
all of these things. So you'll get a
structure and also the apps that you you
need to actually
install.
And then you can in your script figure
out a way to install this on that
environment. If that is a
an Azure VM somewhere, if it's an
on-premises environment, then
figure out how to do that in your own
script. We're not going to deliver these
scripts for you, but maybe you can find
some uh
the ALOps external deployer PowerShell
module can can probably help you if you
want to
to to deploy to a and and on-premises
environment.
You can also optionally use a custom
GitHub runner. So, if you have a GitHub
runner that actually is on the inner
inside of a firewall at a customer site,
then that GitHub runner could be set up
for running deployment to that
environment if you don't want to use the
ALOps external deployer or
other scripts for doing doing that.
That's
optionally something you can use as
well.
So, let's have a look at how to how
these things are actually set up. Let's
just click on this one.
And we can see the deploy to custom
here,
which is
in one of my repos. And if we click
actions here,
go to the update version here,
we'll see that this one deploys to two
environments, custom and QA.
And the custom one will run my script,
which just outputs the parameters here.
And and then I could have done whatever
I wanted to do with that one.
In settings, how this looks is really
Let's go and look at ALOps
settings. We have a deploy to Q&A here,
which is continuous deployment true. And
we have a deploy to custom here,
which also have continuous deployment
equals true.
The environment type is custom. The
environment type is SaaS.
One deploys to SaaS. One deploys to
this script called deploy to custom
and prints out those things.
So,
that is the beauty of
the newcomers in
in deployments. So,
the entire module was like revamped and
and and
we hope that this is something that's
useful for you to
to deploy to to the environments that
you need to deploy to.
So,
next up, pull request status check.
Whenever you're running a
pull request,
we've had a few different iterations of
how the pull request handler should be.
In the beginning, we had the CI/CD
um
workflow to handle pull requests. And
then later, we created a pull request
handler itself. And today, I think we we
we still have the pull request handler.
And and and that one, we now have a
job called a pull request status check,
which you can use
in your
GitHub
uh settings. If you're If you're setting
up um
If you're setting up What are they
called? They're called rule sets. Well,
let's look at that because
Yeah, let's just click this one and
actually see the rule set. So, whenever
you set up a repository, you want to set
up
um
some some rules about who can actually
check into this repository, who can who
can run my scripts, and who can What
security do you have? And and all of
these things. So,
um
let's call them rule sets in in GitHub
today. And and you'll you can activate
them, and you can give them a name, and
you can see who can actually bypass this
and stuff like that. But in the end, you
have branch protection. And and as part
of that, you could require a pull
request before merging. Um in this one,
uh
you would say how many reviewers and
stuff like that. And on require status
check to pass before merging,
you could create you could specify a job
here. The problem is that
in the old days, you would have to like
find a job and and and you couldn't
really find a good job in the pull
request handler because we're using
matrixes to to do the build. So, the
the the the the job that we added was
the pull request status check and you
can just select that as your
uh brand as your job to
to wait for completion uh as your
required status check. So,
with that, it's much easier to to set up
these rule sets and require whether you
like um
yeah, require review from code owners
and stuff like that. I will create some
documentation that describes all of
these things from a Business Central
perspective and also uh our recommended
rule sets in in Business Central and and
and why uh these things are uh as they
are.
Let's go back to this one.
Um
yeah, that is the job that you need to
determine whether or not the build was
successful and the PR can be merged.
Let's have a look at compiler folder and
Linux.
We are on a mission to make things
faster, easier, and cheaper for you.
Uh that is one of the mantras of AL Go
for GitHub. We started out creating
something that was easy to use,
but we also want to make it faster, we
want to make it easier, and we want want
to make it cheaper. Uh faster and
cheaper is the same thing because you
pay for the minutes that you use the
runners.
If it's faster, then it's also cheaper.
Uh we also in the end want to be in a
situation where people don't have to
work with self-hosted runners and all of
these things, but just run all the
builds on uh GitHub hosted Linux
runners, which are uh
fairly cheap. Um
It is like the the difference in price
between uh
Linux and Windows runners is is
I mean, Windows runners cost the double,
and Linux runners are also faster. Uh
and with the compiler folder feature, we
can actually we can actually do some
some things that makes building goes go
much faster than that.
Today, or yesterday,
um
the run pipeline job is really a
do-it-all job. It builds, publishes,
runs test, performance test, and and it
creates a Docker container, and and like
everything goes
um
in in in in one go. So, it's kind of a
black box.
Um we'll split that into a build job and
a test job, where the build part can run
on on faster and cheaper Linux runners
using compiler folders feature.
Uh
that's a new functionality that allows
AL Go to build
apps without containers, and allowed
GitHub to cache artifacts.
Um
And yeah, GitHub hosted runner Linux
runners are half the price,
and uh they are 33 approximately percent
faster than the Windows runners. So,
there's a lot to gain. Let's Let's have
a look at
where we are today.
So, we we we we haven't split up like
the building and testing. It's still
like the run pipeline is one big black
box.
But you can actually set some some some
settings that makes you take advantage
of
the new functionality. At some point in
time, in a future version of AL Go for
GitHub,
these things will be set behind the
scenes, and we'll just use the new way
of building, and then like testing will
be done in separate jobs and stuff like
that. But today, if you want to like try
out how fast it goes when you're
building on Linux, you can set these
settings. So, do not publish apps means
exactly like the settings says, do not
publish the apps. If you say that you
don't want to publish the apps, then
there's no need for a container. If you
If you want to actually try and publish
the apps to a service tier, then we
either need an online environment or a
container or an online container or
whatever. So, so but for now, if you set
do not publish apps true,
we know internally that that we we don't
need a container for anything. If you
then also set use compiler folder to
true, then we can deduct that that we'll
be able to do everything without
containers.
With these two settings, you can now set
runs on and GitHub runner to Ubuntu
latest, meaning that
every single part of your CI/CD workflow
will now be running Linux. You will not
be spinning up a single Windows machine
in that one.
Um note, of course, that do not publish
apps will in effect disable running
tests, which is the reason why we didn't
like default these things. We'll default
these things when we have testing in
place that can run in separate jobs and
stuff like that.
Let's actually have a look at how this
looks and
what the performance gain is. So, this
is a repository under freddy.dk called
Linux,
where I did a few uh tests. Let's look
at the actions here. I started out the
repository creating a new app, and it
immediately kicked off a build called
new PTE. The commit after adding this
PTE, it took 16 minutes to to build.
Looking at at this one, like looking
into the actual build process here,
which is 14 minutes and 34 minute
seconds, uh the run pipeline piece
is the one that takes the most time. And
if we click this one and say
view timestamps here,
we'll see that
um um
going through here 49 40 50 50 and
suddenly like 54 pulling generic image
takes 4 minutes creating a container
takes 7 minutes. So, 11 minutes of these
14 or 12 minutes actually goes for
downloading a Docker image and creating
a container
on these on these runners. So,
we would think that if we running those
on Linux without containers, we'd be
much faster.
And this update algo setting, if we take
a look at this
chart to see what did we actually
change? As we can see, we do not publish
apps, use compiler folder, runs on
Ubuntu and GitHub runner
Ubuntu click actions
and we'll see that this build actually
took 4 minutes and 42 seconds. So, it's
quite a bit faster, 12 minutes faster
than the other build. Let's have a look
at what actually takes the time here.
Um
And 3 minutes and 4 seconds for the
build
and 1 minute and 25 seconds for the run
pipeline
and the determine artifact URL takes 51
seconds. This is actually where it
downloads the Business Central artifacts
to the runner.
Um and then there's a one step here
called cache Business Central artifacts.
Meaning that if I run this build once
more and I of course did that, then it
takes 3 minutes and 38 seconds. So, it
goes an entire minute faster.
Looking at this,
determining the artifact URL
actually takes 48 seconds still.
But,
uh
the cache Business Central artifacts now
take 5 seconds and the actual building
takes 22 seconds because everything is
already cached and we just need to
to build that. So,
uh we can still speed up the determine
artifact URL, I think, because I don't
think it downloads anything here.
Um
that's probably querying for artifacts,
and we need to make that faster.
Um but as you can see,
there's a lot to gain by switching over
and running uh
building stuff without containers,
building stuff where we are able to use
the GitHub cache to actually cache our
artifacts uh right here. So, so that's
what we're doing uh and and and we'll
save a lot of time on that. And the
difference now is that let's just say
that that we have or that not just say,
but but we actually have for a free skew
of of GitHub, there's like 2,000 minutes
included for free of of of runners. Uh
that is that equals to 1,000 Windows
minutes. If every build takes like 20
minutes, then that's 50 builds. That's
not a lot, right? But if every build
takes three Linux minutes, and you had
2,000
uh minutes there, then that's quite a
lot more, right?
Um
so
it then the price of additional minutes
is suddenly
uh a little more digestible, and and
maybe you can you can just use the Linux
runners instead of of using time to set
up your self-hosted runners and all of
these things. So,
that's where we're going. At some point
in time, these things will be default,
and you'll be able to run using the
compiler folder, and and you'd be able
to also
uh run on on Ubuntu and stuff like that.
Um the GitHub runner, you'll always be
able to to use a self-hosted runner if
you want to do that.
Um but but we'll recommend the other one
at some point in time.
Another feature that was added was the
use GH token workflow.
That's a strange name for a feature, but
the This is about overcoming the
limitations of the GitHub token. Uh and
what is that? Well, every single
workflow that creates a pull request or
a commit into your repository now will
have a small checkbox saying use GH code
token workflow for pull request
commit. The reason for this is that
there's a um actually there's a link to
that here if you click the see more.
GitHub says that triggering a workflow
from a workflow is not possible using
the GitHub token. Uh meaning that if we
run a workflow to update the version
number in your repository, it's not
going to trigger a build after that, but
you want to trigger a build. So, you
have to do that in a manual step. The
problem with not triggering a build is
that you you might end up um
actually having changed a lot of things,
and then you don't have a build with
your new version number, and that's
that's problematic. So,
with that checkbox, you'll now be able
to say use the GH token workflow for
these uh
for these functionalities,
and then
it will be allowed to actually spin up
another
uh workflow from that. So, let's have a
look at how that actually looks.
If we just create a new repository uh
this GH token workflow repository here,
and
I run the create a new app,
and I specify use GH token workflow
true.
Let me go here and say create a new app.
Run that, and I I click this one, say
use GH token workflow true.
Doing that
will cause this one to run,
add the app, and trigger a pull request
build.
If I do not check the use GH T work
token workflow,
then it will
uh
like this one, just run the workflow,
but not trigger a pull request built.
If I
ask it oh actually this one creates a
pull request. This one was a direct
commit, which is it is allowed to do
with a
GitHub token. This one is creating a
pull request and that is not allowed due
to some settings
in
actions general
in the bottom here, allow GitHub actions
to create and approve pull request.
This
This I can click this one and then I'll
the GitHub token
is allowed to create an approve pull
request, but it's still not spawn a pull
request built based on me running that.
So, it'll it will still just create the
pull request and then when I merge the
pull request, it will of course run the
build. So,
the option now is to
click that one in order to have GitHub
actually run either a commit build or a
pull request built based on
your
changes to the repository.
That's actually all for
the features that were included. Let's
have a look into a few features that
we're working on right now
and and and what they are
and and
what's cooking.
Um there's no promises, no dates.
I know that it looks like everything is
done,
but we might still like pull the plug
and say we're not going to ship this at
all.
But let's have a look at two PRs that
are out there today. The one of them is
a BCPT test result viewer.
Um
and basically you can see there's a pull
request here. If we click this one,
we'll actually be able to see the
description of this feature
and you're welcome to
to actually have a look at what we're
working on right now. There's a draft
pull request called BCBT test report and
you'll see this is the description of
it. This is how it looks and here some
to-do's. They're all checked. Some
partners actually said, "Uh, that looks
nice."
A lot of of commits and then some tests
running and stuff like that. If you want
to look at the source, then there are 10
files changed and you can actually go
and um add your comments if you want to
do that.
Um
now let's look at what it actually is.
It is a
uh there's a template repository
supporting that. So, if you take one of
your test repository, don't do this with
your production repository
and say update Algo system files with
this result,
then you'll have that functionality
right in your repository.
Uh I have a repository called freddy.dk
BCBT test.
If we have a look at this one and click
this and click into the CI/CD workflow,
click in the build, click here.
We'd be able to see in the summary
section
uh
down here, this is my test results and
this is my performance test results and
we'll be able to see that it uses a
baseline called BCBT baseline.json
um
to to see whether there's any
regressions or anything like that in the
performance or the number of SQL
statements run. Um so, it's a feature
that that we might
add soon. Um but yeah, let's give us
some some feedback on
on whether this would be a good
addition. Uh
you can define baseline and thresholds
uh in files in your repository and then
it automatically runs the performance
tests and and gives you the results
after either a CI/CD build or a next
minor or next major, or test current
build, or whatever. And you can schedule
those, of course.
Um
The last one, customize AL Go for
GitHub. Well,
uh it's something that I've I've talked
to a few partners about. The partners
that are kind of
I think 80% of partners would not need
to, like,
change anything.
Uh they'd be able to use AL Go for
GitHub as is, and and would not need to
to modify anything. But there's a
certain number of partners then that
would like to use AL Go for GitHub, and
then customize a few things. And then
there's partners who would say, "Well, I
my customizations are
way too vast. I can't use AL Go for
GitHub for anything." And then we'll
point to a either AL Ops or Alpaca, or
other solutions out there.
Um but but for the for those who want
to, like, have like
serious
um usage and and and and add some stuff
to AL Go for GitHub that we didn't ask
ask for, but we didn't think of.
Uh there actually is a PR open now, and
whether we're going to merge it or or
include this functionality, I don't
know.
Uh but the PR is here.
And again, you can see the description
of what this is and and how to use it.
Um it it allows you to have a repository
with a
with a template your own template
repository
which points to then the AL Go PTE or
the AL Go AppSource. And it it describes
here how files will be taken from one of
the other area. And then there's a link
to one of my repos that
that contains this. So,
if you want to test this out, again, one
of your test repository, do not use your
production repository for that.
Uh you can you can update AL Go system
files with Freddy DK AL Go at custom.
Um
I have created a small
indirect template repository called my
indirect PTE template.
Uh
and I've customized that. And then I've
created a test repository called
FreddyDK customized. And I have
um
ran the AL Go for GitHub updates in that
one. Let's have a look at what this
actually is.
Uh skip verification on that.
So,
this is my my indirect PTE template.
If we look at the
this one at customizations and settings,
then this is the PR that added like I
added some some settings to
to specify in AL Go settings that I want
to use the compiler folder and and not
publish apps.
And I also added a job called custom
job/my job. Uh I added a
a needs that the build job needs that
job. So, I've integrated this job into
my CI/CD pipeline.
Uh I also added a custom step after the
settings and one before the build and
one after the build. Uh and and those
are in my indirect template repository.
So, my indirect template repository now
now contains some customization of
of um of of folders and stuff like that.
It also contains a
a new BC container partial script. That
is the script that creates the container
when you are running like uh
tests and stuff like that.
Uh
which I also have as part of my indirect
PTE template.
Now, I also have a customized repository
here. The customized repository, let's
have a look at what that actually
contains.
Uh we also had some customizations in
that one. And let's have a look. I here
created one called custom job
prepare deploy, which was like in front
of the deploy and and the deploy step
would would require that to be done. So,
I could do stuff in that one. Uh and
that was also a change to the CI/CD YAML
file.
I also have a custom step before build
here from the repository and a custom
step after the build from the
repository. And we've added those to my
repo now.
Now, this
customized repository
I now want to move on top of the or to
use my
my my PTE indirect
um
template repository.
And this pull request is the effect of
the update AL Go system files
pointing out
my indirect
uh template
and to use as that. Let's look at the
files changed here. And it finds out
that the settings in  AL Go, we
have actually added version strategy
in the
uh indirect template repository. So,
added settings will also be transferred
to the repo by update AL Go system
files. If you already set the settings
in this file, it will not.
In the  AL in the AL Go settings
here in the repository settings,
um the settings that we had from
the indirect template repository are
also transferred.
Let's have Oh, the the new BC container
was added because that was new.
The CI/CD has changed. The prepare
deploy is moved
uh down to the bottom.
The custom job my job from my indirect
template repository is added here.
Uh my prepared job will need the build.
And this one will need initialization
and check for updates. If If a look at
the built,
uh then it adds the custom job my job
here. And if we look at the um
at the deploy, we'll still have the
custom job prepare deploy in here. So,
we actually now managed to merge the two
um the two custom jobs into this
workflow.
Let's have a look at this one where we
had some some steps. We had like a
before built from the repository, and
now we got a before built from
the indirect
template as well.
Now,
if there is already a
a a job with the same name in the
repository that it comes from the
indirect repository, it will be
overwritten. It will assume that it
comes from the indirect template
repository and update that like
everything else is updated from AL Go.
But, if you have like new jobs that are
not named the same as as
as jobs that are that are from AL Go or
from the template repository, then these
will not be overwritten and actually
stay where they are. And they'll be like
run after the other. So,
let's have a look at how it is. So, the
uh before built
from the indirect template repository is
run, and then the before built from the
repo. And after the built from the repo
runs first, and then after the built
from the indirect runs after. So, it
reverses the order after and before.
So, looking at this,
it gives you an an the opportunity to
create your own
your own template repository based on AL
Go for GitHub. So, you just you decide
when you want to uptake new changes to
that, and these changes can then
be be transferred to
uh
to your repositories automatically, and
you can add changes to that and stuff
like that.
So, this is one way of doing it.
Uh you could also have a fork of AL Go.
Uh there are different ways of doing
that and and we're not sure whether we
are going to select one or the other. If
you're seeing this listening to this
video,
uh have a look at the functionality.
Give us some some some feedback on
whether you think this is a good idea or
whether we should just go with forks and
and and those things.
Um with that,
thanks for listening and have a
good rest of your day.